mmm tell me before we get started just
you know off off camera kind of thing
what's happening with the world summit
if anything well they kind of changed
function in that they are really the the
only active members now are Troy and
Robert but they're together as far as I
know and they've been traveling around
the sort of western United States
talking to different groups and you know
the whole thing has become about rather
than peddling their own product it's
about getting everybody on a similar
page you know there's all these activist
groups all these protest groups and they
want to say that hang on hang on don't
worry too much about your specifics we
all basically want the same thing so
let's get together yeah so they've been
doing a lot more traveling and a lot
more meeting whereas previously we were
all staying where we were and having
lots of meetings with the same people no
so they're doing pushing pushing the
outreach side a bit more than anything
really but they've done a lot of
developmental work and I'm ashamed to
say that I haven't really kept up with
it in the last couple of months so I was
pretty keen so I was pretty keen to
become a part of them involved in that
but yeah it just felt like it either
didn't know where it wanted to go or
wasn't really heading there very quickly
because you know those I was supposed to
be the moderator on their forum there
and I you know I went on there I put on
an opening welcoming message kind of
thing and it's the best of my knowledge
still now today not one person has
signed up for or left a message on that
forum you know what I mean so yeah I
thought the idea was really exciting you
know and and what Troy and Robert are
now doing going around trying to get
disparate groups to realize that
actually they're all on the same team
and they need to unite if they want to
have any if they want to have any effect
I mean I think that's I think that's so
bad I think as a valuable thing do you
know a guy called Eisenstein yes
cost him I haven't met him personally
but I know through his books we'll see
in any of his videos but he yeah have
yeah he talks about that that you know
you've got you've got people who you
wouldn't think are in any way connected
but actually they are they're fighting
for the same thing so the environmental
activists and the I don't know the
campaigner for education for dissing
orphans or whatever you know what I mean
they're they're they're they're doing
very different things they're they've
got very different causes that they're
actually they're doing the same thing
they're fighting for a more caring
sharing world if you'll forgive the
awful turn of phrase you know what I
mean the same team in in in that sense
yeah and yeah it says one of his things
is to try and get all of these different
kinds of people to realize that they're
that they that they do have that common
thread you know what I mean that they
don't see the same kind of change in the
world yeah yeah extend your example
there I actually found myself saying the
same thing at an event not that long ago
and I forget the context but in fact
even us and Greenpeace and the neo-nazis
actually at the root of it want the same
thing don't they and of course we've
just had those awful you know that
Christchurch terror terror attack listen
to me a guy shot some people in a mosque
in Christchurch you know
so just cinders making hay over it but
the end of the day you know the guy just
was worried about the future wasn't he
you know really well will we have access
to resources in an increasingly scarce
looking future yeah I mean I don't know
they would articulate it to themselves
in quite that way but no I but I agree
the source of the the source of the
whatever it is the the rage the fear
that whatever it is that brings that out
of people I agree with you it's that
yeah hmm so yeah I'm feeling a little
bit a little bit stuck at the moment in
that you know I'm in Spain and I'm
trying to sort of reconstruct my own
life along along different lines you
know what I mean
kind of feel that until I've done that
not sure how effective an agent of
positive change I can be in the world
while I am still ensnared in the same
kind of stuff myself you know so ya know
I'm a big admirer of yours Richard
you've been fighting a good fight for a
while now and you never seem to lose
your appetite for it you never seem to
lose your motivation it's very
impressive I'm funny how often I say
this but you know one catches up with
lots of different people not that often
and every time I I'm fascinated by the
rhetoric that comes from conversation
rather than from deliberate study or
sort of methodical development just
because most of my work is talking to
people and I'm amazed at what comes out
and so I love sort of unscripted
conversations where we just kind of see
how we get on and that's when the good
stuff comes out and fortunately much of
my work in Greymouth is based around
having conversations on the street with
ordinary people it's not high tech it's
not high leverage it's just sort of face
to face one or one or one on a small
group of very organic conversation and I
think that's where the good stuff is you
know it's non planned it's not intended
it's just see what comes out and I think
there's a subconscious element to that
you know where your subconscious brain
is 90% of your brain can be capacity or
something isn't it yeah yeah it's crazy
and if you couldn't access that material
then you'll do a much better job I think
well the thing is we do access that
material all the time but because we're
so convinced that all there is to us is
our conscious you know our waking
consciousness army you know what I mean
because we're convinced that's all there
is we don't pay attention to our
intuitions and our feelings and our gun
reactions stuff like that and that's
what those things are that's our
subconscious which has access to all of
that additional data it's sending you a
message saying don't do that something's
wrong here yeah yeah I really believe
that that intuition and gut feelings is
exact
that is your subconscious trying to
communicate with your conscious I really
believe that yeah yeah I watch the great
gavel Matt a lecture the other day where
he said exactly that and how frequently
they are in conflict and he our audience
you know raise your hand if you've ever
had a gut feeling and gone against it
and later regretted it and conversely
how many people had got a gut feeling
gone with it and regretted it and now
hardly any hands do you think ok my god
let me down there but it's but yeah it's
definitely rare and you don't feel as
bad about it right because at least you
followed you're done ok it fucked up but
at least you followed in that oh that
was the right thing at the time yeah
yeah sorry sorry what I was building up
to there what I frequently find myself
saying to people is how's it going
haven't seen you for ages Richard and
with utter sincerity I frequently say do
you know what I think it's going better
than ever
more positive sorry this is in answer to
question you know you keep you seem to
keep going but I'm I'm constantly
refreshed and sort of goaded on by the
positive results that we're seeing and
and so it just it gets better and better
actually and I'm more positive and more
optimistic now than I've ever been you
know in the last 10 years and I've been
up there plenty of times but I'm it's
it's an ever ascending pathway you know
we just seem to get closer and closer to
what we all what we all aspire to you
know and every even I mean forgive me
are we recording it it records
automatically so we're recording the
half thing and then I can yeah because
so obviously some subtopics are very
emotive and it's gonna be quite you've
got to be careful not to upset people
you know it's very very easy when
everyone's so jumpy but even the mosque
attacks in Christchurch were indicative
a change or at least the response to
them was indicative of a change in the
sentiment of New Zealanders as a whole
previously well previously there's
frequently been a sort of a New Zealand
very generalized attitude that all that
kind of thing goes on in the rest of the
world that's all because they're mad
it's because they're in sis or because
there are Americans or because it's the
crazy British we don't do that here in
New Zealand and now we do and so what
I've really been up against in the last
10 years is the sort of naysayers who
have got this position that oh it's all
fine you just need to work harder you
know and the anomalies that we witness
overseas aren't really real that's just
something that happens in these funny
places where they're all fucked up yeah
but it doesn't happen here and when
these things start to happen here then
the few and it's amazing I said whew the
remaining naysayers who think that it's
all going to be fine and we if you start
exporting coal again and we can still
expand dairy and sell more wine and
we're gonna create jobs and we're gonna
have green technologies and green
tourism and you know it's everything's
ok those that relatively small now
proportion of the population is feeling
increasingly isolated now that there's
been you know 50 people shot in one
incident that big an impact on the
general sentiment in the country at
large I mean obviously beyond big so the
the reverberations have gone out well
beyond the incident itself yeah yeah
very much so
very much so of course with some abandon
is that first time something like that
happened in New Zealand
oh yeah it's only of that scale it's
using some kind of thing yeah yeah yeah
yeah and so what was it a couple of guys
just walked into a mosque and opened and
open up with automatic weapons did those
guy one guy seem very well-planned of
course dude really embarrassing for the
police and the secret intelligence
services who missed the whole thing this
guy had been all over the world
traveling visiting extremist extreme
right-wing white supremacist type
organizations
material he had a website and a blog and
they missed it and this guy yeah I mean
weapons there's guns everywhere here I
mean I'm bit and I don't know but I bet
there's more guns per capita they're out
there are in the United States it's
crazy the guns here yeah in the US I
heard a stat recently in the US there
are more guns than pets yeah that an
astonishing step I mean God you know in
the I don't know what it's like in the
US with pets but in the UK I would say
on average every single household has a
pet or two you know what I mean and he's
throwing and dogs
parrots rabbits guinea pigs generally
hamsters you know I can every households
got a couple of pets so yeah that's an
extraordinary number of guns and you
reckon it's worse than New Zealand I
mean obviously not the absolute numbers
but per capita is I guess because of the
lots of people have land right and so
they need the guns as protection I get
will stop yeah yeah yeah yeah Sonny I
mean it's one of them it's funny because
it's one of the things that makes this
country excuse me sort of great and
pivotal actually in what we're doing and
why I think we're gonna succeed in
becoming the first money free country
sorry
long angle of approach there because of
the original aspirations of the first
settlers and I don't mean the Whalers
and the seal hunters I mean the wealthy
educated and aspirational British mostly
that came in so the late 19th century
they weren't economic refugees they
weren't fleeing terror or persecution
they were looking for a better life in
the nation yeah they were starting to
have second thoughts about the colonial
Imperial March of British aspirations
across the world you know at gunpoint
and so we have the Treaty of Waitangi so
they effectively did a deal with the
natives and granted them considerable
rights which still very significant
today we're talking hundreds of millions
of dollars but it's a nice is more
accurately previous invaders right
yeah yeah the end of the day I mean this
is this that wiped out the indigenous
people who know yeah yeah they don't
really like to be reminded of that but
it you can sort of get silly but they
were it was definitely different when
they came to New Zealand and much of it
was to escape the hierarchy and the
class divisions that were prevalent in
you know 19th century England so we have
a few things like the quarter acre plots
no one could build a house on a site
that was smaller than a quarter of an
acre which is enough to have a pig and a
few jokes and grow a few fruit trees
kind of thing and they're still of
course they've all been built there's
now 31
a B C and D on every bloody plot you
know in the towns but that that was the
aspiration so that everyone could be
self-sufficient and also things like
access to the countryside and the water
waves particularly is a thing called the
Queen's chain which means basically
anybody can go anywhere within a chain
you know cricket field length of any
named waterway Center so even when
you're just driving around the
countryside if there's a little creek if
it's got a name then you're allowed to
go into that Creek and hunt and fish and
camp there gather firewood and that's
all over the country and they fiercely
defend that right and that's very very
important to New Zealanders to retain
those freedoms of access and it's this
came from hunting didn't it and so
bizarrely in this country even the
poorest people can go and hunt big game
and feed themselves they can go fishing
and they can go ride dirt bikes in the
countryside for example which in Britain
a very exclusive pursuits you know to go
any sort of decent fishing or hunting is
hardly accessible to anybody actually
unless you're very wealthy or very
well-connected
depends where you live I mean there's
some really nice fishing rivers in Wales
and you can get a license which allows
you to finish on I believe any of the
rivers and relatively inexpensive yeah
so I think it probably depends on where
you are there there is some good visual
well you know I mean this is one of the
one of the problems that we hope to
confront right with with with the change
of with the change of paradigm is the
degradation of things like water to
waterways you know what I mean you can't
just most waterways you can't just go in
catch fish you know what I mean stuff
there shellfish especially you can't eat
poisonous yeah yeah yeah and that's a
getting a massive driver hit making life
easier for us Neela no no it's an
international thing extinction rebellion
if they made it over there yeah I'll not
not physically but certainly own over
the Internet yeah absolutely
they got a a decent kind of target or
are they do bit morphic climate change
that's their that's that that's their
that's their thing so they went they
blocked up various different routes in
central London with placards and boats
and various differences they glued
themselves to the front of the stock
exchange I mean it was it was at least
initially for me it was quite inspiring
you know what I mean to actually they
actually see people mobilize and
organize and commit to getting arrested
if necessary you know what I mean to do
you know to go and send out a message
but I've since been watching a little
bit of you know the sort of alternative
side of it on the Internet and it's
quite interesting the backgrounds a
couple of the leaders of it you know
they were they work for NGOs which were
financed by telecommunications and
energy companies and so and also
watching a few things a couple of good
points have been made people saying
things like you know if you look at
previous protests look at the anti-war
protests look at protests for gay rights
LGBT rights that kind of thing you know
these are marches that I've been on the
million mask March I go on there every
year and you know you are very very
carefully channeled as to where you are
and are not allowed to go by the police
you know I mean they don't let you just
stand in the middle of the road and
block traffic so now come these people
are allowed to block Marble Arch lots of
Turkish and I park corner for ten days
you know I mean
now come with no real pushback
whatsoever from the police they block
five bridges London a couple of weeks
before they're right again no real
pushback from the police and we're not
talking about tens of thousands of
people you know what I mean we're
talking about a few hundred a couple of
thousand at the most you know it could
be managed yeah exactly people one of
the phrases I heard was that they're
pushing against an open door and you
know within 24 hours of their 10-day
protest coming to an end they had
assurances from Jeremy Corbyn and from
Michael Gove that that they would meet
with them and you know enter into good
faith discussions and you know their
three demands were that they wanted the
government to declare a climate change
emergency immediately like a national
emergency kind of thing and to set up
people's assemblies up and down the
country who would consult on how to best
deal with the problem of climate change
and so yeah I've got a couple of
problems with it number one climate
change I don't like the term I had a
conversation with Nick not very long ago
it'll go up on the money free channel
soon and he made a very very good point
you know if instead of calling it
climate change we call the environmental
degradation yeah this this would be a
very very much more encompassing term
you know because I don't care how
certain everyone says you know 97% of
climate scientists agree bla bla bla bla
bla what they actually agree on is that
the world is warming right that the
oceans are warming and the carbon
dioxide levels are increasing this is
what they agree on but actually there's
very substantial disagreement as to
whether carbon dioxide increases precede
or suckseed temperature rises because
oxide there's 50 times as much carbon
dioxide iddin know this until recently
there's 50 times as much carbon dioxide
dissolved in the oceans as there is in
the atmosphere right and as the oceans
get warmer they are their ability to
hold carbon dioxide decreases the
solubility decreases so as the oceans
get warmer they kick more carbon dioxide
into the atmosphere right and so what a
lot of climate scientists are actually
saying is that they believe that the
carbon dioxide Rises may be a
consequence of warming
and not a cause of warning right and
there's no doubt that the oceans are
getting warmer but it is that which is
the cause of the Condor so to attack
carbon dioxide levels is to completely
miss the fucking point right and anyway
even if even if and also the other thing
is we produce something like 35 out of
700 Giga tons of the carbon dioxide that
the earth cycles through every year
right so it's like less than 5% of the
total global contribution is made by men
and I get the idea is a delicate system
and it only takes maybe a couple of
percent or upset to embroil that what
sorry I sidetracked myself there I was
gonna say something else
well are we are we focused on the right
thing I think it's what's exactly right
that was exactly my point and and so
that by focusing on carbon dioxide we
are being distracted from and/or in a
way prevented from doing anything about
a lot of the other ecological
catastrophes which are very definitely
very certainly going on right under our
noses you know what I mean it really it
started to worry me I heard one
conspiracy theory guys say that the end
game here is to convince everyone that
the threat of global warming cut human
carbon dioxide cause global warming is
so immediate and so catastrophic that we
have to you know rebuild our entire GM
entire energy and transport
infrastructure away and the only way to
do that is to take all the money out of
your pension funds I'll let the dog in
yes I mean I I've got these five
parameters that if there's one thing I
quote most repeatedly it's probably that
dog hello dog and the first of those
parameters which we've fairly recently
died as a species is is the letter C so
I probably come back to that climate
change but I immediately pounced on
people say I don't really want to talk
about climate change and we don't even
need to it's not really relevant at this
stage you know did man cause this etc
the other day you know just if you're in
a spaceship don't
rubbish you know in in amongst the air
that you're going to breathe and that's
all that really matters there's plenty
of other reasons not to do things that
may or may not claw caused climate harm
and they're all driven by money at the
end of the day and I always feel these
arguments you know we immediately kind
of get onto a Anti poisons or
anti-abortion or climate change argument
and we we've already lost the point and
we can argue and fall out about it and
send each other emails and build
websites about it
go on protests already missed the point
you know just cinder and car all in
Paris patting each other on the back
about what they're gonna do about the
evils in Facebook yeah and they've
already missed the point
you know and all that energy all that
angst and dedication will go into
something that's actually a symptom and
not a fish just gonna use exactly that
word is attacking symptom of causes
that's exactly right that's exactly
right
all of it and yeah I mean climate change
is just the latest one I tend to agree
with you if we didn't do things so
fucking stupid Lee and wastefully then
we wouldn't be having to worry about
these things you know thing yeah many
people the education of our children
were to include an appreciation of the
fact that we are deeply connected to in
fact we are birth ultimately by the
planet bringing worse we include this
over and over and over again then people
would act very differently so yes sorry
you were going to say something
interrupts yeah yeah well again it's
television is in and it gets quite easy
to back up you know we need to get
people to think beyond the superficial
ah there's been a shooting ban guns
reaction yeah and ask you know okay just
stop a minute back up and think well why
did the guy want to shoot anyone in the
first place why do we have threats to
our climate why do people hunt whales
why do people beat their wives you know
don't just have better surveillance in
houses to prevent you know to catch them
when they do be their wives its we're so
reactive it's almost child it's worse
than child like a
but here it's very very obvious because
there's so few people and they're so
intimately connected especially on the
west coast where you know my campaign is
going on and I think there's a much
shorter link between the cause and the
effect of what people are doing whereas
I dare say in Britain or Spain or
something you know bigger more developed
deeper civilization shall we say people
are much more disconnected from the root
causes of the problems that they
experienced was here they're very direct
so here we see dairy farming which is
our biggest export and that crops
everything up basically the sale of
basically milk powder overseas that pays
for basically everything you know that's
the short version but it's disastrous
for the animals for the farmers and for
the environment and the water and people
know people see that very clearly and so
if we want to address that those harm
things that we see that you can't eat
the food in the in in the water you
can't access farms anymore because
they're all like electrified prisons you
know because a huge corporate owned now
most of these dairy farms they're not
family-friendly farms that they used to
be and it and the depression and the
isolation of the farmers and their staff
is horrific
you know the suicide rate among farmers
is amongst the worst in the country
and they're all going into debt horrific
Lee and of course the product that it
produces isn't even really intended you
know in natural terms for human
consumption anyway so the whole thing is
flawed from start to finish but it's
very easy to point it out here because
we're a relatively shallow civilization
no in that regard that dairy actually
serves no intrinsic purpose except to
get money yeah absolutely and if we it
doesn't actually contribute towards the
manufacture of computers or electricity
or food or
gleans you know they're completely
separate and if we didn't do dairy that
the land and of course it's all the best
land in this country could basically
refer back to wilderness because we
don't need it the food that New Zealand
exports is extremely expensive I mean
even Kiwis can't afford it so the
Bangladeshis definitely don't get any of
it it's very high high-end very high
margin niche products for rich people
not for hungry people and so that the
actual and and this is difficult for
Kiwis sometimes the actual produce of
New Zealand serves no genuine purpose on
the world table it's only for rich
people it's just to bring money into
it's just to bring money and just just
playing devil's advocate here I mean
obviously I'm on the same team as you
right but just just for the sake of
playing devil's advocate
so what extent does the money that these
that these trades generate and bring
into the country allow New Zealanders to
buy goods from overseas that they might
not otherwise be able to acquire
entirely yeah
it's the only way we can do that and
that's one once people get to that
stage I tend to especially on the first
conversation I tend to leave them alone
because it's a great if you've got that
far then you're well on the work well on
the road road to seeing that we're going
to be better off without this money
thing so and if it's a funny question
actually I really always enjoy it what
about our imports and exports and
there's actually about eight different
answers to that question and this is
where the face-to-face conversation is
so important because if you're talking
to an older person will say well look in
the 1950s when your when you came over
or when you know when you were growing
up we didn't have imports at all we had
Morris minors came on a boat every eight
weeks and if you were very well you
could afford one but in fact we made
everything that we need here how bad was
it
and for an old person actually we don't
need all that crap at the warehouse and
then these trying selling Chinese
rubbish that goes straight to landfill
we don't even need the imports anyway
I'm talking to I don't know what I don't
know what I mean for example electronic
goods it would be a good one you just
mentioned showing electronic goods I
mean how much of that do you manufacture
cuz I mean certainly in most of the
Western world all of that manufacturing
has been outsourced to Vietnam and Korea
and China and so on you know I don't
know that we have the capability to do
that shit anymore no but it's funny when
you really talk to people they're not
even that sure if we want it anyway
again especially on the west coast where
well they don't have their laptops well
there's a lot of pushback because it's
not brought anything it's not boring
anything tangible and it's not brought
anything good and most people think or
frequently I get it was better off
before we had them loosely to talk to
people looking down at they scream yeah
I'm not sure I mean I'm not you know I I
have some sympathy for that view but I'm
not sure that's gonna fly on a global
scale I'm pretty attached devices you
know laptops and phones much as there's
many awful things about in particularly
in the social media sphere I mean these
things also have the capacity to be
incredibly powerful tools for good right
for education major
activity I mean they they they they can
be incredibly powerful tools for the
elevation of the of the spirit man they
don't have to be destructive I mean that
I agree they largely are right now but
that's a false of the way we use them
not of the not of the technology itself
yeah yes then I'll say a leveraging of
the negative aspects of our current
system yeah exactly it's in their
interest exactly to have us to have us
jump every time a little message comes
through because it might you know might
be selling us something we want
[Laughter]
something that they can convince us that
we want yeah so okay so as to two ways
of thinking about that a third way is
back in 1803 when New Zealand adopted
enfranchisement voting for women they
didn't worry about what the Saudis would
make of it
yeah they thought it was the right thing
to do this is and I would absolutely
especially in greymouth on the west
coast actually and I yeah it's a whole
other conversation which I'm glad your
manual this probably is the leading edge
of human civilization here this place
and so what we do may seem a bit out
there too how she say less civilized
countries but it may well be the right
thing but we shouldn't wait for their
approval before we do it and so this is
like a spearhead of progress and there
will be unanswered questions but in the
short term we can manage without brand
new iPhones you know and short term and
I think because of the nature of change
and also the exponential rate of
acceleration of change
even if the fact that we're talking
about this today means that there's a
knock-on effect and just jumping forward
for a minute if New Zealand went money
free in September 2020 which is still my
kind of favoured day actually for this I
do and everything I do my experience and
I don't do much else reinforces that but
if that happens then Australia
you know our nearest neighbor won't have
waited in the 19th century to see what
happens and of course the rest of the
world is so intimately connected that
when a positive change or indeed a
negative one takes place in one place
because of that technology it can be
spread around the world very quickly
just give it a quick example of you know
talking about climate vulnerability
let's say everybody on the planet
certainly anybody of anything like any
sort of influence now is aware of
climate vulnerability all eight billion
people and that news has traveled around
the world in you know probably half of
our lifetimes or less yeah it's gone all
around the world and that's some of the
worst news that manatee has ever had
whereas the prospects of a
resource-based economy is probably the
best news that humanity has ever had in
all of eternity so how long's that going
to take to get around the world and I
can't see the Australian saying don't
know we like our capitalism it's all
great over here in New Zealand they've
suddenly left into a 21st century
utopian paradise like overnight and
they've solved their climate their
health problems their animal welfare
their mental health they've solved them
overnight should we do that so I don't
think the rest of 20 is what that's nine
months from now that's nine months when
I'm in court I would love to wake up I
love to wake up on the morning of when's
your election and this next one is
October the 12th February 20
20 I assumed you meant that was that was
assumed that was a general election so
why anyone depict that white why did you
pick that particularly well it came out
in a conversation with a group actually
in an Auckland sort of summit that we
had a couple of years ago and I loved
graphs you know my background is in big
aviation and engineering and aircraft
operations excuse me and we do a lot of
trend plotting using graphs and
mathematical models to try and predict
the future so we're trying to work out
how long can that engines stay on the
wing of that airliner before we have to
pull it because of a crack in the
turbine blade or a breakdown in a
bearing you know you don't to pull it
too early these are expenses a bit of
kit but by the same token you don't want
to pull it too late you don't want a
neck so there's a lot of sophisticated
technology and it happens in all big
industry you know ISO 9000 is all about
trying to assure quality not just
control quality but you know quality
assurances so if trend plotting and what
we've been doing with both I'm going to
layer up some graphs now when you're
trotting trends of social breakdown
mental health challenges environmental
challenges all the things that are going
wrong in the world and if you also at
the same time plot the growing awareness
of solutions then you see that they
start to coincide at a point in the
future and absolutely they're
exponential and anytime you get near
anything exponential it gets really
exciting really quickly yeah
and it's very very important that we
don't use historical precedent to
predict future rate of change hello yeah
no absolutely absolutely are you
familiar with Terence Mckenna
oh it sounds familiar but remind me he
spent his life investigate
seeing both personally and as a medical
man the actions of psychedelics and
towards the end of his life he gave an
interview no but he was a really well
respected I mean he was he was the man
you know what I mean he was then it's
really articulate really funny you know
it'll be really easy to listen to anyway
he has this theory which he put forward
shortly before he died that time itself
is accelerating and by that he means
that time what is time other than the
distance between events right you know
did fine is punctuated by the example in
time if there's nothing going on
then there is no time right if there's
nothing happening if there's no saying
is that as evolution proceeds more and
more and more stuff goes on more and
more levels of organization are reached
more and more greater and greater
complexity greater and greater novelty
and so it's just more stuff going on
right and there as a consequence time is
speeding up and that is also an
exponential thing and so I mean
unfortunately this falls down a little
bit because he was one of the believers
in 2012 you know whatever it was
December 2012 was gonna be the you know
like some transformative transformative
thing I mean I've never had never bought
into the sudden transformation thing you
know what I mean like you wake up one
morning and all of a sudden everything's
different I I've never bought into that
everything's a process right it may be a
chaotic and messy and turbulent one but
but nevertheless it's it's a process
yeah the GR you you say you're from my
knowledge of physics particularly
chaotic systems transition from one
equilibrium state to a different
equilibrium state is not possible
without a highly chaotic turbulent
in-between phase so do you know that do
you see the truth of this equilibrium
you know the money market equilibrium to
an RBE tight equilibrium do you think
that can be accomplished without a great
deal of
Yulin mess in the middle wow what a
feast
so I'll backtrack slightly to an
interview I did here actually in 2012 on
my birthday bizarrely with a very wise
reporter from a newspaper and we they
did a big article and on the money free
proposal and she really liked it me I
was really thrilled you know to get that
much I've got a big chunk of the
newspaper it was fantastic
my first decent outing in the press
really um but and she liked the idea but
she said I think it's gonna take a
massive catastrophe Richard to bring
this about
and that bugged me I mean this is seven
years ago that's between itching away at
me for years but when I started working
on the west coast I suppose about a year
ago which is I mean it's only three
hours drive from here we're right in the
center of the South Island so right on
the top you live on both the west and
the east coast effectively when I
started working on the west coast which
is a very very different region to the
rest of the country I realized that this
major catastrophe that people I think
she was right had to go through to
realize that something's really got a
change and it may be asked that has to
change it that major catastrophe
actually doesn't necessarily need to be
shared at the same time so it may not be
a 911 or a Christchurch mosques shooting
it may be the fact that your daughter
took her own life or all your mother
died of cancer or your business
collapsed and you lost your home that is
your 911 that's your personal
catastrophe and because of the West
Coast's precarious history and position
in loads of different terms nearly
everybody there has been touched by
tragedy in some way whether it's a flood
and there's a lot of social problems
there are a lot of economic challenges
and a lot of climate change challenges
and they're very isolated and they know
all about tragedy we have
horrific mining accident eight years ago
29 guys died in 2010 and you know that
shouldn't really happen in 21st century
mining in a first world country
shouldn't happen anywhere but you know
that's unprecedented in the modern era
to have things like that and it always
happens on the west coast so these
people have been through that massive
transformative experience and thus are
ready for change and I think you see it
was intrigued me as you've said there
needs to be a period of chaos between
the money world and the no money world
but of course we're grey creatures
aren't we and so we already have a lot
of experience and activity in the no
money world anyway yeah because we don't
charge our dog you know we don't charge
our family for toilet paper and we do a
lot of volunteer work in the community
we if someone falls over in the street
we just help them we go to libraries we
don't own shopping trolleys we just use
them and we take them back we hire cars
we hire hotel rooms you know we're
actually quite used to a sharing type
economy and environment and in fact it's
not as alien as it seems and I don't
think it'll be a in fact I still have
said this a long time ago I think that
the transformation will be unopposed and
it will be almost effortless actually
and we'll just ease into it overnight
and again we're going to be very careful
using historical precedent of change to
predict future change everything's
different in the 21st century and you
know a revolution can be I think if
Jacque fresco said a revolution of
consciousness yeah it doesn't have to be
of collapse before before the Venus
Project or I'll be able will be yes but
I think we seem quiet talking from the
perspective of history that you know big
change has always been accompanied by
chaos it collapse in the past I wasn't
being guided by history but more of an
understanding of the nature of complex
systems that they say you know
complex systems defined as lots and lots
of individual parts but whose behavior
affects the other individual parts and
human right is a perfect example of a
complex system right they tend to settle
down into their own a career and they
find internal methods of organization
amongst themselves right and and they
settle down into an equilibrium state
but they're capable of many many
different equilibrium states but move
shifting from one to another always
involves a transition through chaos and
while you're in that chaos there is no
way to predict what the next equity
briam is going to look like you know
what I mean now I know that we have
agency and when we're talking about
purely physical systems like turbulent
flow of air for example the individual
particles in that flow there do not have
agency they don't have you know the
abilities whereas we know it's a little
bit different but nevertheless on a mass
scale that we are human society very
much is a complex system and is
therefore bound by the rules of them as
explained but as explained by chaos
theory yes yes however and I've never
said this before don't you think that
that chaos because we are precipitating
a change of mentality nothing else we
just have to change our perspective that
that chaotic period is actually where
many people are now and some of us have
been through earlier than others with
our midlife crises that could be we
could be in that chaotic period right
now and I think I think actually make a
very good point that could be exactly
what the explanation is that we are in
that right now and which is real I mean
that's Trump that's brexit that's the
rise at the farm that's the political
correctness and identity politics
everywhere generally the inability of
governments to respond to even the most
basic needs of their people anymore yeah
Congress doesn't even try and pretend to
actually represent the people the u.s.
anyway give it up even on the pretense
of it you know I mean you know it's all
so yeah I think I think I think you
actually may very well even though it
doesn't feel like it because we're
talking about you know one human life or
a decade or whatever in terms of
evolutionary time of civilization is is
nothing
right and so yeah you're absolutely
right that's exactly what it is we're in
that period of chaos right now
yeah I mean a lot of people know the
next if this equilibrium is broken down
we're in a period of chaos we don't know
what the next one's gonna look like yeah
no no and a lot of people were obviously
Everett very evidently actually in
different places in that chaotic period
so it is like a mass upheaval of
humanity with effectively you know the
blood and the carnage and the burning
and the fighting of a conventional
revolution slash invasion slash
insurrection but it's taking place in
our heads isn't it and so people are
depressed and frustrated and violent and
alcoholic and dysfunctional because of
that internal what they haven't gone
through the revolution yet so they're
still in the fighting pitchforks burning
stage whereas you know those of us I
guess have been thinking of started
earlier I guess for one reason or
another divorce
parental bereavement midlife crisis etc
started and and and now see the fruits I
suppose on the other side something like
that yeah well I said I think we hit a
really good point here that's yeah
co-creation and it's fantastic action
yeah only by conversation can you again
that I mean we didn't make that up did
we that just came on its own no no no I
can assure any of you is that this is
entirely unscripted and prompts you
Richard like we know each other a little
bit we haven't spoken in quite a while
though that's good stuff yeah and I mean
that's something amazing that that
technology has enabled hasn't it to
allow you know to be broadcast you know
I mean I've gained a huge amount of
perspective you know broadening of
perspective and deepening of
understanding of all sorts of things by
listening to exactly this kind of thing
converse
between people between in you know
experts in their fields who are being
questioned by or in conversation with
someone who has enough of an
understanding about what they're about
they can ask them sensible questions and
guide it for the layman you know what I
mean without letting them go and you
know it's French it really is that I
don't know if you know the comedian
called Russell Brand he's one of the
he's become one of the best interviewers
I know on the internet I mean he's great
he does a fantastic rapport with his
guests he gets really very people
talking about really interesting things
some of it really out there some of it
quite mainstream you know what I mean he
seems to be completely non bigoted
Indian if you know what I mean in terms
of who he'll talk to and what he'll talk
to them about you know and I love this I
love this kind of thing Jordan Peterson
I've been listening to quite a lot and
although Suzy strayed into the world of
politics he pisses me off but when he
talked psychology when he talks
mythology you know this kind of thing
you know he's got a lot of valuable a
lot of valuable stuff to say in Jordan
halls another one have you heard about
him he wrote what was it called a common
what the name of the document was it was
an essay after Trump was elected he's
written a series of them sort of an
analysis of the state of society and
he's very much on your page that we're
that were in a time of chaos and that
the blue church as he calls it the blue
church being the old established
institutions the blue church is unable
to cope with the need with the
circumstances of the new world things
just changing so quickly and in
opposition to the blue church is the
Reds or the Reds
religion that's it the red religion is
of is in opposition so we are part of
the religion right so the red religion
is this urgency which is coming about
and it's manifesting in all sorts of
different ways and the insurgency
doesn't have that doesn't wield the
power of the blue church right the blue
church still controls all the money all
the political institutions all the
weaponry nor I mean that's still the new
church but what the red surgeons what
the radius urgency has is the ability to
move quickly and adapt quickly and
change quickly
we pop up one place and the blue church
in its cumbersome slow but powerful way
stamps on that but before we long before
that's happened is popped up over here
it's like whack-a-mole you know what I
mean the blue church can win this game
in the long run but at the moment the
blue church still holds all the all the
big weapons you know what I mean both
literal and metaphorical the blue church
still holds only weapons and and then I
really like this analysis that feels to
me like you know the red insurgency must
inevitably win right cuz it's the new
thing you know and you know it's the
evilly the the the the the red
insurgency must win and the blue church
has no hope of once and for all finally
forever stamping out the red insurgency
it can't be done right and so however
strongly it tries to repress it sooner
or later it must come through and as I
say that feels to me to be a pretty
accurate analysis of where we are right
now yeah yeah yeah I've written it down
I'll look him up he sounds good again
I'm always looking for New Zealand
points of difference because it is so
different here it's hard to imagine how
different it is to anywhere else in the
world actually and when it comes to I
love that blue church that's excellent
all the old news yeah he's really sings
and talks it's such a a very very very
high level for me anyway I have to
rewind quite often you know excellent
yeah that's good that's good yeah yeah
see New Zealand the blue church is not
that far away
and I frequently you know like weekend
before last I spent time with three
members of parliament two of them
cabinet ministers no just out in the
country a little local event that's what
you can do here these people are that
accessible that it makes all the
difference and even if you don't know
them personally you will almost
undoubtedly know a relative of this so
people you know I often wonder if
Theresa May and so on you know do they
actually exist I'm not suggesting that
they don't but you don't see politician
on you can see it it's not just a reason
they although she is particularly bad as
it would be so many senior politicians
when they asked a question you can see a
question they weren't expecting right
they don't have a scripted ology you can
see the wheels turning okay what can I
say here what's that going to look like
what's that you not I mean how is that
going to be Percy brother just answering
the question just can't do it there and
I feel sorry for them I mean Russell
Graham has said this as well as a human
being they are a human being right and
you have sorry for them that you can't
help it I mean no one forced him to take
that job right but but nevertheless in
question yeah and that's the beauty of
New Zealand I cut by chance actually
stumbled upon a 1980s Prime Minister's
autobiography in a free stall actually
so wasn't widely read but but I like
reading political history especially
when it's kind of pint-sized you know
and so I started me on a bit of a train
and when you start talking Prime
Minister Bill rolling for example he
used to teach in the village school here
that kind of thing I've met of we've
only lived here 15 years I've personally
mate - 2 or 3 sorry Prime Minister's and
I mean who the heck am I you know and
I've frequently been on stage with
cabinet ministers and things and they
are very accessible and you know that
our children go to the same schools that
kind of thing it's very very important
and reading these books by and about the
Prime Minister's it occurred to me that
a the person that wrote them if it
wasn't autobiographical
knew them extremely well and had lived
kind of alongside them for their whole
life whereas I bet there's a thousand
books about Margaret Thatcher written by
people who probably weren't even alive
when she was in power there's that
detachment but what I really loved about
it again was the common theme that they
all talked about the same people and the
same incidents and the same cities and
that you could see a direct cause and
effect to things like the anti-nuclear
rigid legislation the anti-apartheid
movement things that actually change
history for this country can be traced
back to conversations and activities
that took place amongst people that are
accessible and that truly exists and
that live there now and so suddenly you
realize that the whole thing is actually
still controllable by a logical rational
means whereas I would say that
legislation under let's say anti-hunting
legislation in the UK you know why did
that really come about you know is it
pressure from overseas or from the
judiciary or from the people or from
vested interests in Europe I mean who
can say why things happen yeah and yet
all the people's angst and all that
misery
the reality is 95% of the population
don't really give a shit you know what I
mean not affect them directly don't give
a shit yeah yeah but but it's a good
example of how political correct
and mobilize large numbers of people
because you know most the people who are
demonstrating on one side or the other
have no direct connection to hunting at
all you know what I mean it's an ideal
of an ideological position they take and
it's not based in their own personal
experiences or whatever you know they're
just all hunting is evil all people who
want to ban hunting our evil what's the
what's the 5g situation like in New
Zealand are they are they talking about
5g they're they talking about cuz I'm in
New Zealand in many ways would be an
ideal place for right I feel populations
in one sissy that's all you've really
gotta cover is Auckland you know that's
more than half your population down in
there well if I can start with yo yes
it's just such a hotbed here as well for
fuck's sake it's so ridiculous but if I
can start with broadband because you
know we had dial-up internet in the
early days and then the National which
was a conservative right-wing government
decided that we should have broadband
and it was going to be expensive because
of our population you know the way they
spread out the geography and everything
so the only way to pay for it and I had
this argument with a serving cabinet
minister in public on a public stage
saying that they had to sell off our
public utilities the airline and the
electricity generating and transmission
companies to pay for superfast broadband
because we've got to stay competitive
with the rest of the world and I said at
the time and I think I was quite proud
of it you know off-the-cuff profound
statement that superfast broadband is
that actually it's merely a Trojan horse
to ensure that every little girl on the
west coast of this country who we're
traditionally people have gone to escape
this kind of thing she will have a smart
device in her pocket so instead of
skipping around the field barefoot in a
dress she will now be checking on her
makeup her teeth her body shape her hair
the Beast will get to everybody and it
has you know and it's horrific and I
think 5g is just more of the same you
know and yeah of course even more
intrusive yeah well yeah but there's
radiation issues with 5gm it's a whole
different bandwidth to previous is
connectivity to previous communications
yeah yeah yeah it's a much much shorter
free it's a much much shorter wavelength
of radiation that they're using and
there has been zero testing of the
effects of this radio they're just
rolling it out not having tested it at
all and they're a lot of listen I don't
know I don't know I I haven't only
testing I haven't even seen any data but
it seems to me entirely reasonable that
testing should be done before a system
like this is rolled out that that in
principle seems entirely reasonable to
me yeah I'm got time to test have they
in the modern marketplace Russia's 4G
seems pretty alright to me I mean I live
on I don't have a hard-line internet
connection you know I live entirely on
4G and it's fine it's fine you get the
occasional bad patch you know to me but
it's absolutely fine so I don't see what
the Russians with 5g fortunately I
fucking know where they're not gonna be
put you might be here for a very long
time is not the population I mean awful
people here don't have internet access
as it is the average age is like 65
after people here at least half of
people here don't have internet
connections as it is yeah yeah fantastic
however be careful because I I've quoted
in the past that you know in many parts
of remote Africa they got coca-cola and
Marlboro a long time before they got
medicine and water you know
the tentacles of the monetary system
reach a very very long way yeah but it's
easy and cheap to deliver Marlboros and
coca-cola it's not easy and she blew the
5g it's a different different different
thing altogether yeah and again I mean
5g Marlboro country Cola they're all
distractions and they're all symptoms
and I don't think any of them would
exist without the monetary system and so
when everything becomes free and
everything that becomes entirely
voluntary
then well then we'll actually get what
we want because we'll be the ones did
installing it and if we
i humanity collectively commands
collectively would demand some fucking
testing before putting this thing
increased likelihood of cancers and you
know and brain to you do some testing
but yeah from the people who are out
there on the scary side a bit what they
are saying is very very very scary
they're actually very short exposures to
this as significant and is way outside
of recommended doses of radiation and so
yeah and it's just being rolled out
willy-nilly but like I said won't affect
me except when I go back to the UK then
it will it will affect me then because
the UK will definitely have it will be
one of the first ones everywhere yeah
yeah yeah yes greymouth may not have it
I don't know so yeah tell you so you'll
tell me a little bit about because I
when I spoke see when we communicated by
text a week or two ago you said that you
thought you might have a genuine chance
of becoming the mayor of Greymouth so
that's why I'm trying everything at it
yeah yeah I think it's the fastest yes
what's your position look like older
heavier still white white and middle
class but very would you call it blue
church yeah coming and to be honest with
you I have a field day with being
onstage with these people in public
because it's just you know at the end of
day precocious or otherwise we're right
yeah and at the end of the day if you
stick with the truth you can't go wrong
and what you said about the politicians
were they you know off-the-cuff question
sort of the trouble about is they have
to balance a million competing interests
every day whereas when you just tell the
truth you know it's like a kid who's
lied in the past you know okay so - who
did break the bars then
[Laughter]
if you tell the truth you can't go wrong
can you the lies that you told yeah
absolutely and and of course the poor
politicians etc so they have this
ridiculous balancing act that in the
resource-based economy' world we do not
have to play anymore you just tell the
truth and the science will guide you as
to the correct response yeah it's not
even difficult and I was astounded the
very first public outing I made at a
mayoral level when I was contesting
their nelson mayoral tee in 2013 and I
had a lovely prepared speech and the
mayor candidates got 5 minutes and 450
people in the audience I mean I was
shitting myself but this is great right
I'm going to talk about spaceship earth
and how it's going to work in a
resource-based economy and I discovered
I mean it's amazing how you can lose and
win in the same few minutes but I
discovered that scripted speeches with
this kind of material do not work we're
not teaching people anything new weirdy
brainwashing them and so everyone's got
their own custom brainwash and you've
got to look them in the eye and have a
conversation of some sort and figure out
where are you stuck with this what's
your personal hang-up with what i'm
proposing because everyone's got a
different version so my scripted speech
was rubbish but when it came to the
questions and answers this big audience
had a lot of questions about health care
about violence about alcohol in society
about jobs pollution I realized that I
had the easiest job of all and
authorized them by far the least
experienced of the four candidates for
the mayoralty
I was able to genuinely put my hand up
for every single question from the
audience immediately without even having
to think yeah start thinking in
money-free terms suddenly every problem
we've got becomes easily soluble yeah
yeah you're free money you're free to
think in terms of like Jacque fresco
said right you're free to think in terms
of do we have the technology do we have
the resources do we have the manpower
yes right let's do it
ok
not is this interest going to be upset
are they gonna let us do it are we able
financing reissue the bronze blah blah
blah blah all of that gone gone
advocates of money however would say
that the necessity to raise finance for
a project is a effective barrier to bad
projects not being undertaken with
historical precedent prove that theory
how many good projects have been
undertaken yeah I would say I guess now
we have the scientific method to it and
at the end of the day you you know even
the most charismatic brilliant
inspirational leader is not going to get
much of a project together if it doesn't
suit the community that it involves and
I would say yeah I guess you're right
into a degree in that the money filters
out the crap projects yeah people aren't
invested something I think is shit right
because they're not gonna risk for their
money on it and so it's a good barrier
to shit not not happening unless it
makes money in which case shit will
happen anyway well that's the thing shit
means now change will not make money no
absolutely absolutely right yeah and
that's the beauty of the resource-based
economy because now you've got a
self-referencing automated process
whereby a the technology assists in the
project so no one has to mix concrete by
hand no one has to dig holes no one has
to hammer nails in anymore
I've got amazing technology to do that
so that's all easy if we want to do
something too easy but you're still
gonna need the time so buying I have to
look for a better better worth the
investment still need a better word the
these money this money thing goes deep
you still need the involvement of the
humans to make it actually - operation
you still need the ability for people to
cooperate collaborate and cooperate on a
large scale
still gonna need to build things like
bridges and tunnel
absolutely hospitals and well maybe
airports but you know the the roads yeah
whatever whatever it might be you know
there are large-scale projects which
still need to be undertaken and which
affects people over a large area you
know what I mean and benefit people over
a large area but then there are also
people it doesn't affect and doesn't
benefit and so I mean this is this is
where I get a little bit confused and
this is where I personally maybe I'm
just smart enough not smart enough to
see it I personally have a problem with
detailed transition plans because I
don't know part of me I guess it goes
back to what I was saying before about
transiting from one equilibrium to
another means that you go through a
chaotic phase and there's no way of
knowing what the next secretary was
going to be looking look like from that
chaotic place and so I kind of feel that
the path to RBE or something similar to
it something that embraces those
philosophies is most likely going to end
up not being anything that anyone has
thought of yet you know what I mean it's
it's something that will emerge from the
collective when there are enough people
working on the various problems that
we're going to encounter and you know
what I mean something will emerge that
has healed yet we don't we do we have no
idea what it looks like no it does take
some Imagineering doesn't it and it's
Collinwood put a she calling Turner from
free world charter who I know I saw your
interview he as he beautifully so
eloquently put to really get this you
have to suspend your disbelief on
several levels at the same time and it
takes quite a lot of mental well
certainly energy to bring that about but
I would say have faith because when we
get to the final product the RB world
this bloody dog you know dog is always
on the wrong side of a door isn't it
you just went out oh the the
self-referencing is massive and at the
moment that the example I use in at the
moment if say that the breadwinner in a
household drives a truck for coca-cola
okay
those big red trucks and they carry
around 50 tons of coke and they deliver
it to supermarkets and towns all over
the country and everyone in the family
if anyone in the country knows that
those kind of drinks aren't very good
for us but because of the money thing
everybody write down the food chain you
know in our local dairy there's 19
coca-cola signs you know just a little
country dairy in Wakefield so it's very
very well promoted although nobody
really wants their children to have it
but nevertheless yeah yeah and of course
right down to the manufacturing and
delivery you know the person that drives
that truck they get paid to do that and
they can thus provide for their family
thank you mummy or daddy that's how we
get the things we need so we kind of
fall well yeah we would drink it but
that's you got to makin gotta do a job
you know fair enough but after money now
the family and the community and the
support structure of that truck driver
who he currently supports with his local
contribution because of the money that
he gets from his job he doesn't need
that money anymore because everything
that he used to buy with it is now
supplied for free so what's the point in
going is he gonna go as a volunteer when
a is taking him away from his family in
his community where he's really wanted
as a human being and be they know very
collectively know that what he's doing
is actually get tremendous society's
health as a whole their faith and in the
community that they're living they're
actually growing plenty of oranges and
apples and carrots and shit like that
and they're making their own juice and
it's much nicer and they don't want
fucking coke anymore they don't need the
truck bow down to go away and no
has rotten teeth anymore yeah but if
suddenly he gets a call and let's say
Westport has had an earthquake and they
need food they need blankets they need
relief goods and machinery because of
the disasters arson disastrous situation
will that truck driver get the support
of his community his family his Society
of course he will
and we've seen evidence of this with the
disasters that happen here every few
months saying that when things go really
really really badly we revert to
communism actually right brilliant yeah
it is brilliant
it's fucking absolutely true yep yep and
the Christchurch earthquakes prove their
enormous Lee I mean the government
completely oh my god what do we do and
we end up with a farm er me they're
called rustic farmers got big machinery
tractors trailers food stores equipment
and they just all these farmers got
together or have a quick ring round of
course they're all related they all know
each other and they got together with
the gear that they needed to actually
help those people out and then about the
same time the student army you know
there's a couple of universities in
Christchurch which you know after the
earthquake there was no classes the kids
well what do we do well let's go and
help these people and together with the
farmers and all their equipment they
basically took over the city you know it
was incredible they went door-to-door
you know the place is covered in mud and
there's all these houses falling down
and no electricity water all over the
place these kids went door-to-door
alright love what do you need you know
wait we're gonna need a tractor over
here to lift this she's gonna need some
food she's got a baby coming and they
sorted it all out on it and it's an
amazing and again a very visit and
recent demonstration of what people do
if you let them you know
and that's a really nice story that's
what I wasn't aware of that that's a
really really nice story yeah and even
what he remembers it like it was your
slits a proper human that's a proper
human you know uplifting story isn't it
yeah I like to think that that's that's
how we behave most of the time given the
opportunity to do so do you know what I
mean that's that's that's how I like
that's I mean you know it's not
something you do but that's what I like
to believe that's my arms a good faith
if you lie here yeah
and that's also part of my chaos interim
segment whereby you know you'll get
little opportunities to dart forward in
the into the future or what I'll be
gonna be like oh we'll hang on in
2010-2011 we experienced it didn't we
yeah and I mean the volunteering here is
astounding you know if you if you chair
a bloody School Committee in England you
get a fucking gong for it don't you
we're here he's doing something like
that all the time and the ambulance
service sent John's ambulance I mean
it's the V and ambulance services 75%
voluntary here as it is the fire service
and you know so people know about
volunteering already and then if it's
quite easy just to extend that so why
don't we make your job voluntary and
then people start to freak well what do
I do
is it does it contribute anything
[Laughter]
another great thing about New Zealand is
the access to data you know government
data we can lead the world in the depth
of that they've got you know they've
been really thorough in there for the
most part anyway certainly better than
most countries and it's very up-to-date
and it's very transparent and accessible
and we did a big survey actually Glenn
tins and I good colleague of mine and
only 27 or 27 percent of all work done
in this country is just managing money
so that they don't actually produce
anything tangible whatsoever well you're
nothing
so advertising marketing sales banking
investment accountancy they're just
juggling numbers and those people can
instantly retire so when therefore we
need sorry what can I do like an attire
and of course you can retire with all
the accoutrements that you gained
through your endeavors previously
because you didn't contribute towards
the manufacture of boats or holiday
houses you had no part in their
construction because that was all done
by people who actually produce things
and of course machines so you can
continue to enjoy your luxury lifestyle
but just please don't go to the office
and predate upon everybody else any
making a massive contribution just by
stopping doing they're incredible and so
because it gets better this is the
fantastic thing about our be when you
start think about it oh my god it's even
better than I thought those people and
we all went to scroll there weren't many
of my school but we grew up with them
you know which kids at college and
things were the ones that got into
finance and banking and investment they
were the proactive hard-working
motivated intelligent driven people and
they still are and they do things that
are offensively successful because it
produces great fruits for then there's
nothing you know nothing wrong with
aspiring to that but once we retire
those people they're not just gonna sit
around and do nothing
what are they don't weekend's they do
fucking social work and community
restoration and environmental projects
don't they they do those now what are
they going to do in their free with
their networks God the other day art
might I've got a great relationship with
my accountants areia and she's been
basically on board it's pretty amazing
for an accountant for Jesus nearly ten
years I mean what a shit what are we
gonna because they're so hard-working
these people they're so proactive and I
think they're gonna be a man
if part of this because the accountants
know everybody the same accountant the
same person can be accountant for an
environmental group a church a school a
village organization the government even
has accountants you know a business a
marketing company you know all these
things they all associate through the
same accountant frequently at top level
you know at principal level in the
organization so flip over to the non
money world and of course these
accountants they always have very big
schemes for fundraising and doing good
in the community I mean I think most of
it well men on the whole actually now
we're freeing them up to use their
networks so when we have a I don't know
let's say we need a new sewage system in
our remote village I'll go to my
accountant not say where can I get the
money but where can I get the resources
he's got the diggers who's got the pious
you hear you talk about because I think
a lot of people in the zeitgeist
movement in The Venus Project and
perhaps in the RBR be a movement in
general see money as an evil and by
extension great anyone who works in the
field of money as being evil so it's
really nice no but it's really nice to
see you thinking that actually they've
got a very valuable real contribution to
making you're quite right to say that in
many cases they are actually the best
and the brightest dollars who go into
these fields and that it would do well
to harness that harness those energies
and intelligence for yeah for better
right now absolutely absolutely no
that's really nice to hear is I can
understand why you are so successful at
this because you you look to find the
best you know you look to find the best
in people don't see everyone as an asset
rather than an enemy it's so rewarding
you know because it's it's sort of
win-win you know you can't really go
wrong with that yeah it seems to every
every conversation seems to be
positively
tributing you know rather than goodies
and baddies friends and enemies you know
and it probably is a bit naive but I do
see everybody is just victims of this
system yeah we've all become horribly
corrupted by it but and especially again
sorry on the west coast where everyone
has such a recent or relevant experience
of tragedy their humanity is that much
closer to the surface and you really
don't have to talk to somebody
especially if you are sincere and
impassioned you don't have to talk to
people for very long before they say
yeah you're right mate we've got to do
something yeah whereas me much of the
rest of the country where I've done a
lot of my street work it's frequently
the people still think they're going to
be okay they still are no we're going to
make it all my daughter's doing great at
university my son's got another business
and you know and they don't they they
won't go there you know the cognitive
dissonance is too strong to dare to
penetration told me might within the
conversation I had with Nick the other
day that for a lot of people I said I
mean I I see it a lot in the UK that
kind of person where you know they've
got a lot invested in in their lives
today they've got kids they've got a
career they've got a mortgage they've
got responsibilities they've got a
family they've got a network of friends
they got membership of the club
bla bla bla bla bla you know yeah our
beers on is a long long long way from
there it's a really really really
radical shift of perspective exactly
what you said before that's
fundamentally what it is a perspective
and once you've made it you look back
and think well that was really fucking
easy but from the other side a bit from
the other side of it it's it's not like
that right it's it's it's yeah so we do
need to be infinitely patient and
compassionate with those who are as you
say victims of yeah they're traumatized
ah yeah its
proto 4matic stress disorder right yeah
okay we often mention gamma left earlier
on I'm a massive fan of his as well he's
all the mess from yeah yeah yeah and
we're in it now it's not postal my
tickets now yeah
but no wonder you can't get their
intention because they're sucking in a
bunker dodging bullets you know so
they're not going to listen to a lovely
country I'm here almost every day I mean
it's not like it's trauma in the past
and it's over and even right no it's
really yeah reinforcing all the time
every day yeah yeah yeah and just going
back slightly to for one of the better
expression to have a therapy session you
know not many therapy sessions take
place in foxholes are they you know
you've got to get out get away from the
danger zone get back to somewhere safe
so they're comfortable have a drink
you know have a use the toilet sit down
in a chair let's talk about where we get
to and when people are so traumatized
they're so superficial they're so busy
did a group you know rushing around
thinking in their superficial top you
know whatever it is 5% of their brain
they do not have the time or the
inclination when you've got a fire
burning in you know backyard paintings
on whereas on the coast they never
really wanted the modern accoutrements
of the 21st century and I try not to get
too far off the topic here but I think
it's frequently I've had all you'll
never get the coasters to accept this
Richard they net they're so resistant to
change and they are resistant to change
but only if that changes bollocks
so many of the changes in the last you
have been bollocks haven't they you know
or you need faster broadband you need
news another pair of shoes you need a
different colour car one the broadband
thing I'm personally on board I remember
tile a tile I was a fucking neighbor
don't you you know yeah go down the pub
and have a talk with someone rather than
yeah at least again these things are not
mutually exclusive right you can still
go down the pub and have a chat with
your neighbor and you can still have
broadband at home so that you can you
know educate yourself on YouTube or have
a
like call with your daughter overseas or
whatever you know yeah yeah no I'm not
I'm not I'm not taking a position I but
on the west coast like they've got a
reputation for being anti progress but I
think with very good reason in that most
progress has been pointless and it's
just sells is being discerning not anti
progress yeah um one of the things I've
really got excited about Cory the most
is that they want to talk and whereas on
the rest of the country but the response
I've got over ten years of doing this is
generally oh that's I love me to see you
cuz everybody knows everybody that's
great
how you getting on you know are well
done that sounds really exciting what
really drives me nutty is good luck I
think this is my cause and it's not your
you know you obviously you're not
consumer trying to change or freaking
inequality that's just my thing because
I know you're busy and then so tip it
off I'm trying
I've got a shoe off lovely to see you
yes flick me an email
I'd love to see the new website and that
as well sorry it's the world that the
West Coast does not live in right
because on the most everybody says hello
to everybody all the time I mean all
they want to stop and talk and so are
you familiar you know so what's that all
about and of course running for me
immediately opens the so why do you want
to be mayor then what can you do here
and off we go and then and then after
that and what is astounding and you
probably won't put this on any video
hopefully is that frequently all I've
done is say hello to their dog or enjoy
the view together or talk about the
weather and they say I'll vote for you
yeah well you'll probably OD you're
probably the only candidate that's
actually true you know been
straightforward human being around them
yeah yeah and I think people something
you said before made me made me think of
a question for you you've got to balance
two things haven't you in your candidacy
for mayor on the
and you got actual responsibilities to
the actual people living there right now
today right that the other and you've
also got a larger responsibility to the
RBE movement because this is a stepping
stone this is a springboard to greater
publicity greater notoriety greater
ability to speak about it in public
right yeah and so you've gotta balance
these two things so to what extent no
let me slightly rephrase that how
seriously are you taking the first part
of that you know your mayoral duties to
the citizens of your town yeah okay I've
known quite a few mayors and we're the
greatest respect to a large degree is a
ceremonial role right they don't
actually have that much executive
authority then another board of the
council kind of thing yes you are but
you're only the chairman and you don't
have a special casting vote you have the
same valid validity vote as the other
councillors who are all elected who are
most definitely well embedded locals and
you don't have any influence at tabling
the contents of what's being discussed
especially here it's extremely
transparent people are very interested
in council activities here I'd say much
more so in the UK again everybody knows
everybody it's all much more local much
more familiar with everybody and so the
mayoral role there's not yeah I mean you
get access to things that you wouldn't
otherwise so when you say it's
ceremonial are you are you sort of
saying that you have no more power than
any other councillor kind of thing is
that what you're saying or they don't
even have as much power as a normal
councillor now you have the same power
as a normal councillor but not much more
only because of your probably more like
to be on the radio or get quoted in the
paper or go to conferences because
you're mayor but you don't actually get
to make any decisions by yourself okay
and of course I don't really know
anything about local government you know
to be bluntly honest it's just no I'm
done this before
an American mayor where you know you're
allocating the resort
to your police department in schools and
so on you know not at all and in terms
of democratic I would say this is
probably the most democratic country in
the world you know that kind of thing is
fiercely defended and very transparent
and yeah as about as good as you could
do it actually know there's an old boy
network but for the most part it worked
fairly well actually but that's changing
because the old boys don't know what to
do
so should you win you would actually be
able to concentrate primarily on role
number two then ie using it as a
platform to publicize RBE to a wider
audience yeah
for a national campaign yes that is that
is that kind of on your on your horizon
new thinking I'll come back to the first
question in a second well of course
we've got the money free party and we've
got general elections in 2020 so that
may be a point of contention for me if I
am mayor do I drop the mayoralty to
become a member of parliament well only
if you win right you wouldn't have to
drop it just to run would you or would
you would you have to drop it just to
run now you don't have to drop it to run
but if you win you do and by then they'd
have to be a by-election which are
expensive and time-consuming and just
annoying and of course there is a it's
happened quite a few times
the locals well in instances that I've
seen in the past and I guess everyone is
different the locals have been really
pissed off at being abandoned yeah
person might with envy I understand that
yeah yeah ah so he's pursuing his own
ambitious yeah yeah I can I get that on
the other hand if you have the people
behind you then it might be saying go on
go for it it's only ceremonial we'll get
we can just get another mere you go on
and all the way son you know so it
probably depends on how things are going
at the time
just to finish off the question yeah
there are plenty of mayoral duties
cutting ribbons kissing babies that kind
of thing but what the way I see it
because I do like to keep things
succinct if possible believe it or not
the the council machine is a big
cumbersome one of many wheels turning
very slowly and the position of mayor
really is just part of that machine what
you do have is the ability to direct
that machine so with the right vision
one can point the machine in the right
direction but we're not going to become
a money free town overnight yeah but you
do by bringing people along with you
right not by telling you and this is
what we're doing but by convincing
exactly yeah and I mean I suppose it's
just human nature but it seems bizarre
to me that once you're mayor suddenly
you have relevance you have Authority
you have that suddenly what you said the
day before now has more very very very
early age to obey Authority to you know
the name of but they're very famously
experiments where you know they had the
person behind the wall who was answering
questions when they got one wrong they
told a guy in a white told the guy to
push the punishment button and it gives
an electric shock to the other person
they turn the button all the way up and
if the guy insists if the guy in the
white coat insists they'll turn it all
the way up to death I mean it's not
actually happening right but yeah I mean
amazing how deep it runs in most people
it's amazing how deep it runs it's an
authority figure it's essentially
absolves you of personal responsibility
by telling you to do something people do
almost anything as evidenced by the fact
that you know I'm sure a very nice young
men I'm happy to drop bombs on villages
during war I mean know what I mean City
uniform on them and give up waters you
know well they're really nice people
most of them yeah
yeah yeah can I can I have a go at why I
think greymouth is the only place in the
world that we can begin this yeah go
just because I do and I've said it in
public now on Facebook and things on a
page it's called love greymouth and it's
just a local thing and there's pictures
of sunsets and dogs and things and it's
very but occasionally we get going with
a good conversation and I've said that I
think this is actually the last bastion
of human civilization because of several
factors one I'll start off with is the
disparity which is really important my
mouth is not the most deprived place in
the world but it probably is the most
deprived place in the world relative to
the aspirations of the rest of the
country so New Zealand as I said it
probably is one of the most civilized
countries you know we have the world
world leading animal welfare legislation
voting for women human rights freedom of
speech you know obviously anyway so yeah
talking about disparity between their
sort of expect expectations' of a nation
and the realities of the lives on the
west coast yeah which i think drives the
change because it's you know worse in
the congo you know than they are on the
west coast but then their expectations
and aspirations are nothing like us hi
so it there isn't the driver for the
change and I think
so we we leave world in bowel cancer a
third in obesity suicide heart disease
we're right up there
legislation as well please yeah isn't it
amazing in this you know it is pretty
amazing place and yet there's all these
ghastly problems and they're even worse
they're exacerbated on the west coast so
they know all about their there but we
have this reputation aspirations
expectations to be world leading yes
over 300,000 children living below the
poverty line in this country and that's
a deal I've totally worn it before and a
bit million so it's basically a quarter
of children live below the poverty line
no minutes and of course no one's got a
couple to do about it not at all apart
from sell and sell more dairy but what
so it's a funny dynamic in that we've
got these expectations we've got the
situation but we've also still got and
only on the west coast we've still got
the human relations that have generally
been lost in the modern world
so most countries with similar
aspirations expectations etc have lost
their human connections so you know in
most towns people don't even know their
neighbor anymore and I mean it of course
many do but that's that's massively
broken down and no one's really got time
to talk to anybody anymore which is huge
on the coast you know everybody wants to
talk and they've known their neighbor
you know because they both grew up in
those houses that kind of thing so
you've still got a very strong community
social fabric that I think has generally
been torn apart in what we call more
civilized nations so the Congo they
probably still do know most and the
people in the village but there
all poor and they're just happy if they
survive to adulthood whereas in a more
sophisticated country yeah they have
higher standards etc but they've lost
the human connections whereas in
greymouth they seem to have retained
those human connections they are the
expectations of a very first world
country but they've got the reality of
almost a third world country and so that
disparity drives enormous frustration
and I guess you couldn't all my say it
it demonstrates that chaos that comes
with the transition from one regime to
the next you know because it's such a
such a bizarre situation you know we've
got all this utter abundance and yet
everybody's struggling even if people
know the Thorpes are too stressed that
they are on bloody drugs and alcohol and
eating all the wrong food and fighting
and and you know just like growing up in
the UK I remember the term from the
1970s intergenerational unemployment you
know and what that hasn't that effect on
a social psyche and so you have this
funny combination of all these different
factors so much it's the sense of not
feeling like you're making any kind of a
contribution to anything you know money
coming in but I mean that
psychologically that secondary I think
yeah yeah yeah yeah except with our
modern devices now you know it is
secondary but of course you can no
longer afford the things that you aspire
to so everyone expects to have their own
jetboat widescreen TV two bathrooms in
every bedroom it all dit so yeah so
again there's a disparity there the
expectation of it very high but the
actual reality is very very low and a
Greymouth sorry gone when there's only
thousand people and there are two and a
half thousand houses of the don't are
not yet connected to the sewage system
in a town know that they're still on
septic tanks and there is actually a
government requirement that started
about ten years ago to update this kind
of thing but they just cannot afford to
do it and I was having a cup of tea in a
lady's house the other day and she in a
1940's house and this is so typical and
it still had the original wiring from
the 1940s and this is very typical none
of these people can afford to fix their
houses up because they haven't got any
money
post health and safety legislation etc
even to get your chimney it you know you
have to put scaffolding up and do a
health and safety assessment oh my god
the cost of that so basically it means
it's no one's done anything the value of
property as a whole has fallen in the
region because there's no work so nobody
will lend them the money to do the work
many people are in negative equity and
suddenly the whole thing spirals down
and we haven't even talked about
earthquake risk yet which is represented
throughout the town itself in that many
many of the commercial buildings are no
longer fit for purpose because post
Christchurch the whole country had an
assessment of the building stock done by
engineers and they realized fuck if we
had quite like that here this would fall
down and who can afford to pay to fix it
up nobody so consequently the businesses
are leaving town in droves because they
can't afford to fix the building that
they're in the landlord can't afford to
fix it insurance companies won't insure
them presumably won't go near them yeah
and in fact that came out the other day
because in Sharia the insurance
companies having a bit of a field day at
the moment because they're shit scared
of the whole thing and when as we
discovered here when an insurance
company won't insure you then the bank
won't lend you the money yeah yeah so
you don't end up living in a house
that's not insured you end up being
evicted from the house because the bank
their investment covered by insurance so
it's doubly bad actually and equally the
general infrastructure in greymouth is
all struggling as well I mean that's
nationwide and I think in the UK to
actually you know underwater pipes
sewage tubes etc what you hope to do
about this crumbling infrastructure I
mean what what would you as mayor as
well because slash mayor be able to
bring to the table to solve these
problems okay yeah two answers and this
is where it's absolutely imperative to
have the people on board and depending
on how on board they are depends on
which which road will travel and I guess
it'll probably end up being a
combination of both but one is if the
people are really behind me and if we've
had the RBE conversation with in half P
other way they're frequently called
feral in breeds but this event that I
was at last two weeks ago was partly in
the celebration of May Day we know which
is a great socialism event globally but
this little village where we had the
event was the original seat of both the
Communist Party and the Labour Party in
this country in the early part of the
last century it was also than the site
of the very first in organized
industrial action in 1908 in New Zealand
industry the very first strike and that
has not been forgotten there are very
revolutionary bunch so to answer your
question there are two things we could
do we can either go money free straight
away and fuck it and then because the
revolutionaries are not just the hippies
in the woods and so sorry
just just pause you for a minute there
so by going money right away you mean or
correct me if I'm wrong but by that I
get that you mean okay so whatever
potholes need fixing so who's got the
trucks who's got who's got the gravel
not the time yeah who who couldn't who
can wield a shovel let's get out there
and fix these potholes and and you know
put noticeboards up and whatever and
recruit people to do the things that
need doing is that is that essentially
what you mean yeah fucking we won't wait
for the central government to provide
the money we'll just go and fucking do
it and there's already a history of
their Amer there's three mayor's on the
coast - by far the biggest one but the
most southern one Bruce Smith is a under
sensor at the moment by the council
overseers because he and a mate when
there's some flood remedial work needed
to be done the hurry they just went out
with their diggers and they're fucking
great big trucks his mate is like 80 and
he owns a big construction company and
they just went out and they just fucking
did it
of course subsequently there was a bill
over 1/2 million dollars for the council
which they then freaked out about
because they hadn't gone through the
transparency
but this is the nature of these Peter no
and because again you know I said
everybody throughout the food chain has
been touched by
tragedy these but they're not over mind
to just wait for central government to
come up with some funding there's only
four roads in and out of this whole
region and they all go through narrow
gorges through the mountains I mean you
could close them off on now love to see
this which would I'd love that you
inspire me man I'd love to when when is
the election October 12th October 12th
today all right I'll try and find some
kind of information service on the
internet where I can get exit poll data
and stuff another way it could go and I
said this in a closing statement in the
newspaper
I was really tough to have the last say
after the very first mayor or my first
mayoral election 2013 my advice they
rang everybody the four candidates after
the election what do you think of the
result and of course she just fucking
won't be wonderful darling kind of thing
it's not a time for being silly you know
you get one closing statement in the
whole show is over I said in the paper
and I and I still quite like it in that
depending on how revolutionary the
people of gray mouth are the other
option is just to borrow the money and
fix all this stuff because we will never
have to pay it back who will lend it to
you oh there's seem to be plenty of I
mean the council debt in greymouth is
about 30 million the council debt in
mutt where I live now in this region is
about 120 million so you think you've
got 90 million you can borrow I mean
this is how we bizarre is and I've got
my one of my favorite expressions is
it'll either make money or it'll make
sense but it won't make burrows you know
again it's part of that chaos theory
you know things make sense or they make
money but if it makes money it won't
make sense so so if yeah bizarrely
entities will lend money to district
councils
because they have a lot of that new
infrastructure that bridge is worth 10
million dollars that Shopping Center is
worth 50 million dollars that's how they
partition getting liens on these assets
I mean if he fails to pay it back today
they're now in the shopping center of
the bridge well I mean which brings
another delightful so version of that is
we won't close the road we will just
have a boycott on bills so from this to
be forward we have a lot of meetings
first but from this day forward we just
will not pay our mortgages rent rates
electricity etc and what oblate what are
they actually gonna do because all the
banking here is Australian owned
basically is the Australian Savings Bank
gonna come here and repossess 10,000
fucking shacks near the middle of no one
what are you gonna do but the mortgage
is definitely I love it with the
mortgages and while you're at it you
could make that argument that was made
in the zeitgeist movie the second one I
think it was that all mortgages are
illegal contracts they are all every
single last one of them fraudulent
contract yeah that's right reminder
through the courts now that's very least
you can make a splash in the papers
about it you know yeah because they are
fraudulent contracts I mean by by the
website the foundation of the Lord you
know I mean where consideration on both
sides has to be put out they are
fraudulent they have no absolutely so
yeah no I like that but I tell you what
I like the first I do the best going
full RBE straightaway I like it right
this is the shit he's doing we've got
there we've got the skill base we've got
them we've got the equipment whatever
you know between us we've got it let's
figure it out man yeah yeah doing that
you're in charge of doing that you're in
charge of doing that crack on yeah and
if you don't do it it's your reputation
mate yep yeah yeah and and half the rest
of the beneficiaries are your Emily so
yeah and one of the things people most
are frustrated about is despite and
these were you know they're coasters
so they have amazing resilience and
initiative and drive you know they're
fuckin it's pioneer country really
they're very resourceful one of the
things that's in it's not only these
disparities these people have enormous
capability you know they're miners
farmers sailors they can do anything and
yet they're fucked because of this
system from outside yeah
they can't even provide for their own
family now despite being capable of
doing anything they can't even provide
for their family because of this fucking
system that says you have to have the
special tokens never mind all the
diggers or the fuel or the chainsaws or
the no no no if you haven't got the
tokens the family stars you know and the
wife leaves and the kids are on fucking
drugs and that has a room happen you
know so they they hurting like man
because of this and when I was getting I
mean I generally I've been at work the
last couple of days doing mechanic work
and I tend to wear the same clothes all
the time
but on the coast they are especially
anti experts from outside in suits here
we go here's another one but there's an
organized so I tend to wear this kind of
thing and I thought off of your video
what should i okay and I've never you
know generally I'll put on a shirt have
a shave
kind of but they don't want shirt in the
shave they want how it sounds to me like
I'd line these West Coast folk yeah you
would yeah they could solid fucking you
know handshake people yeah yeah they
really are
I love going there it's fantastic I just
it's such a boost you know to come every
conversation I come away again
further up the scale of holy fucking
shit we're gonna do this you know and
that's I'm trying everything that
they're it's funny a dilemma between
recruiting RBE supporters and recruiting
voters
for those two things well it depends how
long you've got because I wouldn't want
to go in the newspaper for example and
have to in two column inches explaining
this fuckin communist anarchist hippie
from outside fancies being mayor because
they wouldn't put the material across in
a way that was palatable to most people
whereas if I can have a conversation
with those people then I can guarantee
their vote but you know touch would
basically but it's got to be the right
conversation and it may be as little as
oh my thought what a lovely dog you know
Kay hello what's his name or it may be
20 minutes of profound anarchism you
know having a proper chair but it's got
to be measured and it's very very
personal so and what I've done in the
past you know through bitter experience
is go too far too soon you know we've
all got these again coming back to the
airplanes analogy where you're doing
everything by performance envelopes you
know you can only do so much
it's the same with humans you know we
can talk about a money free future but
don't say don't go blasting right we're
gonna make everything free tomorrow yeah
okay he's lost it he doesn't have a
rational grip on yeah I kind of don't
like the whole money free I don't like
the name money free party people down
the wrong path of thinking because it's
not really about money free is is not
about taking money away it's about
creating a system whereby money no
longer serves a function it just no
longer has a purpose oh is it and once
you get it then you get that but I've
given that you know trying to recruit
may be the wrong word but you know what
I mean yeah yeah if you never like I've
never liked to know no well hints yeah
tell me about it and we fucking done
that for ever since the start you know
with Nick especially I mean I went and
stayed with his family to try and nut it
out and we didn't get anywhere over
there consequently I mean I'm very very
sensitive to that and I'm just going out
for a minute so this is I know if you've
seen the bus pictures of it I've never
actually seen the campaign bus yes this
will cost a fucking fortune by the way
so this is the number plate is that is
that reverse to you is that the right
way around no that's right that's right
Oh how's the future looking and the
website and this is all IRB East so
Institute resource-based there's at the
moment we've got this logo on the side
which is now sort of internationally
I'll say recognized as the money free
logo but not money free party just money
free New Zealand money free France money
free USA well whatever okay
and this work when we get closer to
election time it'll say vote Richard and
a special website that we're building
called coastwise or nzd which is
specifically for Greymouth and this
particular election it's not a global
money briefing at all and then on the
back we've got the whole the big logo
looks great yeah that's really nice you
know I really call out there called bad
boy graphics over in grey mouth
bizarrely yeah so you know been able to
call upon like-minded souls to give of
their time and work free in order to
help you along I guess you probably have
on some occasions and not on others
right yes some stuff some stuff no yeah
yeah actually bad boy graphics are
giving us quite a break but yeah I mean
the materials are expensive for example
yeah I've got my cup of tea then have to
rewind the video to find the tea but yes
so we're very very conscious of and
cautious with using terminology but I
know I mean I've got a pocketful of
different cards you know depending on
the conversation should I give them an
institute card or a money free party
card or a sticker or a money free world
card I mean again it's the brainwashing
it's not about me it's about you
I liken it to a log jam you know in a
creek that's all jammed up with logs why
doesn't your brain work clearly and
rationally like it was intended to when
you were born you know a stream should
just run and if you can have a
conversation with that person you can
frequently pick out just one or two logs
in that jam bush and they're away and it
can take ten seconds or it can take ten
years and then that's but it's again
it's one of the things that drives me on
but especially forgive me on the coast
because these people are so crushed
they're so fucking downtrodden and
depressed when you come along with
something like this they are a flame you
know and that is a fantastic thing to
behold to be part of that setting people
free again you know and awakening all
that lovely energy and passion and
compassion that's been so shut down for
so long it's a profound experience and
it really drives me along you know which
I guess brings me back to where we
started you know the energy comes from
the people not from me you know I get it
from them you know to see to see people
coming alive is fantastic to be part of
it yeah privileged actually not that I'm
likening you to Mother Teresa but I
remember seeing with Mother Teresa a
while ago which she was asked you know
how is it you live in those conditions
and look at all of that suffering
year-in year-out you know how he managed
to do that and she said no you don't
understand you know when I when I when I
look into the faces of these people I
see it is God staring back at me you
know what I mean yeah as far as she's
concerned she's living and exalted like
you know what I mean she feels pretty
able to do what she's doing so you know
it's again back to the idea of
perspective you know yeah it's lovely
having your own mountain water I
wouldn't trade it for anything it's just
lovely isn't it fantastic fantastic yeah
very very rare actually today yeah
well of course that's one of the big New
Zealand arguments is all we should sell
it so and we if we they do they actually
fly it in bottles to China good business
because they can turn a profit while
they're doing it right so it's it's it's
good business that they got the bottom
that Mariana you know the other day and
the Pacific just up the road the deepest
kissed humans have ever gone in the
ocean it's like 11 kilometers deep
yeah and they found they found some new
species and you know amazing all these
glowy what really things and load a
plastic rubbish it's just extraordinary
just makes you think that anywhere
there's water anywhere there's liquid
water there's there's gonna be stuff
wriggling about in it it doesn't matter
where you are yeah it was a pleasure
really enjoyed that thinking and yeah
living in times of chaos I like that I
like that you know I've asked that
question to a few people not on these
interviews but I've asked that question
to a few people and you're the first one
that has proposed well we're in it right
now I like that I like that that feels
right yeah that's great all right thanks
ever so much
yeah it's and keep me keep me updated
with anything and definitely as you
approach election time send me a
reminder that it's coming up because I'm
really curious to see how you get on and
if you do win whether you go full RBA I
really hope so and I'd really like to
see that I'd really like to see that
even if it fails for whatever reason at
least lessons will be at least lessons
could be learned you know what I mean it
could be the first the first proper I
don't know blue church experiment into
RBA because you you enter the blue
church when you become mayor kind of in
a way that's
Church kind of yeah although you are
secretly a member of the red religion in
surging I think one of his other themes
just before we go just made me think of
it talking about him again he I really
like the way he covers a massive span as
far as one simple thing so he goes back
to whenever fifty hundred thousand years
ago when we first became the dominant
species on the planet yeah and we
started going off and colonizing all of
the niches that they were on the planet
and becoming the top red so wherever we
went and so it went in our small groups
until we'd colonized every niche on the
planet and we started to encounter each
other right we started doing how to
thrive to be each other and at that
point we had to figure out how to
collaborate or at least coexist without
killing each other for the long-term
survival of the species right and he
calls that game a everything we've been
doing from that time until now is game a
game a cope with the complexity of human
society of technology of medical
advances blah blah blah blah blah game a
the structures of game a and the blue
church is kind of the key holders for
game a if you know I mean game and so
anyway in game B and you've actually
touched on a couple of the features of
game B during this interview game B is
forming collaborations and networks of
people such that information is passed
around within the group in such a way
that every person who gets access to
that information siphons separates out
the the wheat from the chaff the signal
from the noise you know what I mean and
and passes it on to the others in the
group now that it's been refined by them
to something more useful and so on and
and that the collaboration of the open
and willing sharing of information and
and ideas between this group of people
creates
an emergence thing yeah you know in the
same way that the cells of the body
create the emergent thing that is the
body that individual musicians in a jazz
band create the emergent thing which is
a living piece of jazz you know what I
mean is that that kind of thing and that
game B is going to be centered around
this coherence among people and that
when this coherence can be rolled out
across millions and tens of millions of
people that's that's wellness that's
when we're playing game B and so this
whole competitive money politics power
imbalances all of that has to go because
in order to play game B you have to
enter into coherence with others and in
order to do that they can't be personal
agendas ideological agendas you know
what I mean it's got to be pure it's got
to be clean so yeah yeah I really think
you'll like him he's an interesting guy
I really think you like you yeah cool
all right thanks it easier speech you
keep the other bye bye